Arrays are a way of storing a collection
配列とは、同じ型のデータの集合を
of data of the same type together.
まとめて格納する手段のひとつです。
Let's say we need to store five integers.
例えば 5 つの integer を格納する必要があるとします。
Rather than storing them individually as
個別に myIntA, myIntB, myIntC などと
myIntA, myIntB, myIntC etcetera,
名前をつけて管理せず
we can store them in an array.
まとめて配列として格納出来ます。
We declare an array in a similar way to
配列を宣言するのは、
declaring an individual variable.
個別に変数を宣言するのと似た方法でやります。
However after the type of the variable
違いといえば変数の型の後に
we use open and closed square brackets.
[] 記号を使用することです。
It's important to make the distinction
覚えるべき重要なことは
that an array is not a type but a collection
配列は型でなく、むしろある型の変数の
of variables of a certain type.
集合だということです。
Before an array can be used we need to know
配列を使用する前に
it's length, i.e., how many elements
長さを知る必要があります。長さとは、言いかえると
will be stored in it. Elements are what we
格納する要素の数です。要素とは配列において
call items in an array.
アイテムと呼ばれます。
To specify the length we use the 'new' keyword
長さを指定するためには new キーワードを使用したうえで
followed by the type of the array
配列の型を指定して、
and the number of elements in square brackets.
要素の数を [] の中に指定します。
We can now initialise our array
配列の初期化については
in the Start function.
Start 関数の中で行います。
We can access and initialise elements of the array
配列の要素へのアクセスおよび初期化をするには
by using the name of the array followed
配列の名前の後に
by square brackets containing the index
要素のインデックス番号を [] の中に
of the element.
指定して下さい。
The index of an element is simply an integer
要素のインデックスは integer を指定するのみであり、
with the first index being 0.
最初のインデックスは 0 から始まります。
When thinking of an element's index
要素のインデックスを考えるうえで
think about how many steps away from
最初の要素から数えて何ステップだけ進めば
the first element the one you're trying
アクセスできるか考えます。
to access is. So to access the first element
つまり最初の要素は
use the index 0, since it's 0 steps away
最初の要素から 0 ステップ進んだ位置にあるので
from the first.
インデックスは 0 です。
For the second element use the index 1
二つめの要素のインデックスは 1 と続いてきます。
and so on. Now I'm going to initialise
それでは配列に 5 つの要素があるケースで
the five elements in my array.
初期化してみます。
So that is one way of declaring and
配列を宣言して初期化するには
initialising my array. However, if I want to
これがひとつの記述方法です。しかし、もし一行で記述したければ
I can do it all in one line.
それも実現することが出来ます。
This means that I can initialise my array
すなわち、配列の初期化と宣言を同時に
at the same time as declaring it.
行うことが出来ます。
We do this by using braces as we normally
このためには関数、ループ、 if 文と同様に
would for a function, loop or if statement.
{} 記号を用います。
Between the braces we put the values for our
{} 記号の中に
elements in the order that we'd like them to
配列で並べたい順序どおりに
appear in the array.
配列の値を指定してきます。
This will create an array of five Ints
これで 5 つの integer 型 の変数の配列が作成できました。
just as before, starting with 12
前述のサンプルと同様にして、 12 から始まって
then 76 and so on.
次が 76 であり、その後も続いていきます。
Note that we didn't specifically state
今回は配列の長さを明示的に記述していない
the length this time. This is defined
ことに注目して下さい。配列の長さは
by the number of elements within
{} 記号の中にある要素の数によって
our curly braces.
決定されます。
Arrays declared in this way can still be
このようにして配列を宣言すると
accessed in the same way as demonstrated
本セクションの初めのサンプルどおりに
in our first example, by using.
アクセスすることが可能です。
There are a few things to note about arrays.
配列についてはいくつか注意すべき点があります。
If you make an array public you will be
もし配列を public とした場合、
able to see it in the inspector
インスペクタ上でも表示されるようになり、
and allocate values to it.
値を割り当てすることが出来ます。
So if I save my script and switch back,
もしスクリプトを保存して元に戻ると、
I can see that where it's assigned to an
オブジェクトにアタッチしたときに
object my player's array is showing
player の配列は
publicly in the inspector and I
インスペクタ上で public 変数として表示され、
can assign a length by using the size value.
配列の長さは Size 変数を使用して値を割り当てることが出来ます。
So if I type in a value of 1 in to Size
つまり、 Size の値として 1 を入力すれば
I get 1 element in my array on to which I
配列上に 1 つの要素が出来て
can drop a game object, because that's
ゲームオブジェクトをその上にドロップできるようになります。
the type of this array. However we can use
これは型がゲームオブジェクトであるためです。
the script to initialise it.
またスクリプトにより初期化をすることも出来ます。
Unity has some functions that can help us
Unity にはいくつかの関数により
to do this. We want our players array to
この作業を行うことが出来ます。players の配列には
store all of the players in our scene.
このシーン上の全てのプレイヤーを格納していきます。
The function FindGameObjectsWithTag
FindGameObjectsWithTag 関数は
returns an array of all the gameobjects
シーン上で特定のタグのついた
in the scene with a specified tag.
全てのゲームオブジェクトを配列として戻します。
Since our player gameobjects all have the
player ゲームオブジェクトはすべて player タグがあるため
player tag we can pass this in and get all
すべて渡すことが出来て、シーン上の全ての players を
of the players in the scene. We can use the
取得することが出来ます。
array that this function returns to
この関数が戻す配列を使用して
initialise our new public players array.
新しい public である players 配列を初期化できます。
So simply by doing this we have assigned
これにより、この関数が戻した全ての値を
everything that this function has returned
player 配列に割り当てした
to our players array.
ことになります。
That means that it's collected the objects
すなわち、 Player タグのある
Aaron, Bob and Charlie as they all
Aaron、 Bob、 Charlie というオブジェクトを
contain the tag Player.
すべて集合させたことになります。
Another great feature of arrays is that
配列のすぐれた機能のひとつは
they work really well with loops.
ループとの相性が良いということが挙げられます。
Let's say that we want to log the name of all
シーン上のすべてのプレイヤーの名前を
of the players in our scene. We will use a
ログに残したいとします。
For loop to iterate through each element
この場合、For ループにより
of the array.
配列の各々の要素に対する処理を行うことが出来ます。
Array's have a property for their length.
配列にはその長さに関するプロパティというものが存在します。
This will return the number of elements
これにより配列の要素の数が戻されます。
in an array. This means that if we
すなわち
start our loops iterater at 0 and continue
ループ で反復させる変数を 0 から始めて
to loop whilst it's less than the length
配列の長さよりも短い場合は
of the array, we can perform a number of
そのループを続けるようにすれば、
actions equal to the number of
配列の要素の数だけ
elements in our array.
処理回数を反復させることが出来ます。
What's more, our iterate variable, 'i',
さらにいえば、反復変数の i は
will also be equal to the index number
配列のインデックス番号と等しくなります。
in our array. This will print out a
これにより
sentence that says 'Player Number 0 is named Aaron'.
Player Number 0 is named Aaron という文章を出力できます。
It does this by taking the text Player Number
Player 番号の後に
followed by the 'i' variable, representing
変数 i を続けることで
the number, or index, and finally it
インデックス番号にあたる数字を表示させて、
retrieves the player's name by looking at
最後に、 players ゲームオブジェクト配列における
a particular index in the 'players'
特定のインデックス番号にある player の名前を
gameobjects array.
取得します。
So I'll save my script and return.
ここまで完了したら、スクリプトを保存して戻ります。
I'll press play and here we can see that
Play を押せば、For ループにより 3 つのメッセージがログに
the For loop has logged three messages.
残ることが確認出来ます。
One for each item in the array until it's
配列の要素の最後に到達するまで、
reached the end of the array of elements.
各アイテムごとにひとつづつアイテムがログに残ります。
You can also see that the array is assigned
配列はスクリプトにより初期化されて、
to our public variable in the inspector
インスペクタ上で public 変数として
as it was initialised by the script.
アタッチされたことが確認できます。 (翻訳:gamesonytablet)